{"tossups": [{"question": "The discovery of chicken bones of a specific breed suggests these people may have had contact with the Mapuche people in the 14th century. Naturalist Joseph Banks hired one of these people, Tupaia [[too-pah-EE-ah]], to serve as navigator on the <em>Endeavour</em>. These people used a specific type of outrigger boat known as the <em>ama</em>, which they used to colonize the modern-day countries of New Zealand and Hawaii. The Pacific Ocean was traversed by, for ten points, which Oceanic people whose subgroups include the Maori and Samoans?", "answer": "<b><u>Polynesian</u></b>s (prompt on specific groups like \"Samoan(s)\", \"Maori\", or \"Hawaiian(s)\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "After living in self-imposed exile in Europe, this man returned to the U.S. to marry Eliza Jumel, while using his mother\u2019s maiden name of \u201cEdwards.\u201d Due to this lawyer's previous failed lease of the Bastrop Tract from the Spanish government in present-day Louisiana, he was tried and acquitted of treason. After losing a gubernatorial election for New York, this man challenged a former Secretary of the Treasury to a duel. For ten points, name this vice president under Thomas Jefferson who shot and killed Alexander Hamilton.", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Burr</u></b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first engagement in this war began in Wallachia at the Battle of Oltenita. This war's Danubian phase ended when Omar Pasha defeated Prince Gorchakov at Silistria. In one battle in this war, only the ship <em>Taif</em> [[TAH-eef]] escaped an attack by Pavel Nakhimov at Sinope [[SIH-noh-pee]]. This war included battles at Malakoff redoubt and the Great Redan by French and British forces as part of the Siege of Sevastopol, an effort to capture the Tsar's Black Sea Fleet. For ten points, name this 1853 to 1856 war between Russia and an Ottoman-European coalition.", "answer": "<b><u>Crimea</u></b>n War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During a 1980s dinner Nancy Reagan apocryphally asked what this man has done to be at a White House dinner, with this musician responding \" I've changed the course of music five or six times.\" With Gil Evans, this musical figure created arrangements for the George Gershwin opera, <em>Porgy and Bess</em>. <em>The Birth of the Cool</em> and <em>Kind of Blue</em> were albums by, for ten points, which American Jazz trumpeter of the work <em>Miles Ahead</em>?", "answer": "Miles <b><u>Davis</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "Athenian tyrant Perillos died in this specific manner using an apparatus called the \"Brazen Bull,\" which he supposedly invented. Buddhist monk Th\u00edch Qu\u1ea3ng \u0110\u1ee9c [[THICK KWAN DOOK]] performed this action on himself to protest the persecution of his fellow monks in South Vietnam. Hammurabi decreed arsonists should be executed via this method in his namesake \"Code.\" Christian heretics were most often executed by, for ten points, what method also known as immolation?", "answer": "<b><u>Burn</u></b>ing (accept equivalents like <b><u>being set on fire[a]; accept more specific</u></b> <b><u>examples like [a]burning</u></b> at the stake; accept <b><u>immolation</u></b> or self-<b><u>immolation</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "To create votives of this substance, the Ancient Greeks used the <em>Sphyrelaton</em>, or the \"Hammer Elongated\" method. Despite being known as the \"Iron Man of India,\" Vallabhbhai Patel is depicted using this substance in the tallest statue on Earth, the <em>Statue of Unity</em>. Rodin [[roh-DAHN]] faced false accusations that he used a real person as the mold for his lifelike sculpture, <em>The Age of</em> [this metal]. <em>The Little Mermaid</em> in Copenhagen and <em>The Thinker</em> are cast in, for ten points, which historically valued metal alloy composed of Copper and Tin?", "answer": "<b><u>Bronze</u></b> (accept <em>Age of</em> <em><b><u>Bronze</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The lynching of Thomas Shipp and Abram Smith in this state motivated Abel Meeropol to pen the song \"Strange Fruit.\" The abduction and killing of Madge Oberholtzer by this state's Klan leader, D.C. Stephenson, led to a sharp decline in the second KKK's membership. A Republican senator representing this state interrupted the two non-consecutive terms of Grover Cleveland by winning the Election of 1888. Benjamin Harrison and his grandfather William Henry Harrison both governed, for ten points, which Midwestern state?", "answer": "<b><u>Indiana</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When this group began to overrun the FANK, the U.S. initiated Operation Eagle Pull to evacuate personnel. This regime closed most schools as part of its campaign against the \"New People\" and used a former high school building as \"Security Prison 21.\" This party's government killed over a quarter of its country's population at sites known as \"Killing Fields.\" For ten points, name this Communist party led by Pol Pot that controlled Cambodia in the late 1970s.", "answer": "<b><u>Khmer Rouge</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Auguste Mariette led an effort to clear this monument of debris prior to a visit by the Emperor of Brazil, Pedro II. Historians discovered that several 18th dynasty rulers may have suffered from familial epilepsy due to the Dream Stele [[STEE-lee]] situated in front of this monument. A now debunked theory claimed this monument lost its nose to cannon fire from Napoleon's army during the Battle of the Pyramids. The Pharaoh Khafre is depicted with the body of a lion in, for ten points, which monumental statue in Giza?", "answer": "Great <b><u>Sphinx</u></b> of Giza", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was deemed a \"White Jew\" in an editorial in <em>Das Schwarze Korps</em>, the SS newspaper, after he was named \"favorite\" to head the Munich Faculty. With a set of scientists, including Walther Gerlach, this physicist was detained in England through Operation Epsilon to determine how close the Nazis were to creating an atomic bomb. Albert Einstein nominated this scientist for a 1932 Nobel Prize in Physics he won for determining limits to predicting physical quantities of particles. An \"Uncertainty Principle\" is named for, for ten points, which \"Father of Quantum Mechanics\"?", "answer": "Werner <b><u>Heisenberg</u></b> (or Werner Karl <b><u>Heisenberg</u></b>; accept <b><u>Heisenberg</u> </b>Uncertainty Principle)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "The \"Joe and Jerry\" show took place in this election year, which featured the first formal vice presidential debate. The loser in this election year used a \"Rose garden\" strategy to present as a leader compared to his opponent. That same candidate sank in the polls in this election year after claiming \"there is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe.\" For ten points, name this U.S. presidential election in which Gerald Ford was defeated by Jimmy Carter.", "answer": "<b><u>1976</u></b> United States Presidential Election", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country's first president was Gr\u00e9goire Kayibanda, who persecuted an ethnic group known for its cattle-herding. Under his successor, the RTLM radio station and <em>Kangura</em> magazine incited hatred towards that group in this country, referring to them as \"tall trees\" to be cut down. After its president's plane was shot down in 1994, this country suffered a series of massacres until Paul Kagame's [[kah-GAH-mehs]] \"Patriotic Front\" seized control of the government. For ten points, name this country where a genocide occurred against the Tutsi people.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Rwanda</u></b> (accept Repubulika y'u <b><u>Rwanda</u></b>; R\u00e9publique du <b><u>Rwanda</u></b>; or Jamhuri ya <b><u>Rwanda</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The \"phantom time hypothesis\" claims that in this century, Pope Sylvester II and Otto III made up three centuries of European history to legitimize Otto's claim to the Holy Roman Empire. In this century, Callinicus [[kah-lee-NYE-kuss]] of Heliopolis created the incendiary \"Greek Fire\" weapon. Byzantine Emperor Heraclius lost the possessions of Roman Syria and Egypt to the Rashidun Caliphate in this century. Islam emerged during, for ten points, what early medieval century?", "answer": "<b><u>Seventh</u></b>th Century (accept the <b><u>600</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Despite winning this battle, one commander's resignation was called for by the public, leading the president to reply, \"I can't spare this man; he fights.\" W.H.L. Wallace's men managed to hold the Hornet's Nest during this battle, which was won after the arrival of the Army of the Ohio under Don Carlos Buell. William T. Sherman emerged as a war hero following, for ten points, what 1862 Civil War victory for General Grant in southwestern Tennessee?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Shiloh</u></b> (accept Battle of <b><u>Pittsburg Landing</u></b> before mention)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A person from this colony opened a ferry service at Blue Rock, sparking a territorial conflict that was only resolved by royal proclamation from George II. Thomas Cresap was from the colony that became this U.S. state, which used the Necessary and Proper clause to attempt to tax a federal institution led by James McCulloch. With Virginia, this state agreed to give up territory to establish the District of Columbia. The U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis was founded in, for ten points, which Mid-Atlantic state on the Chesapeake?", "answer": "<b><u>Maryland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "While serving as a captain in the German army, Otto Jaekal [[YEH-kul]] excavated for these animals in the mines of the occupied Belgian town of Bernissart. The rivalry between American scientists Edward Drinker Cope and Othniel Charles Marsh led to the \"Bone Wars,\" a period of discovery of this general class of animals. The ancient Chinese believed to have found \"dragon bones\" after discovering the remains of, for ten points, what general class of reptiles which include <em>T. Rex</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Dinosaur</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Dinosaur</u></b> fossils; prompt on \"Reptiles\"; accept <b><u>Iguanadon</u></b>s before \"Edward\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Description acceptable</em>. Jimmy Claxton was perhaps the first person to successfully breach this regulation despite being promptly fired a week later. After speculation that Armando Marsans and Rafael Almeida broke this regulation, managers assured the public that \"they were as pure white as Castile soap.\" Branch Rickey and Bill Veeck both attempted to break this regulation, which was successfully broken when both Larry Doby and another player appeared on rosters. Jackie Robinson was the first player to break, for ten points, what regulation in Major League Baseball?", "answer": "Baseball <b><u>color line</u></b> (accept Baseball <b><u>color barrier</u></b>; accept descriptions about how <b><u>Black</u></b> baseball players were prohibited from playing in the MLB)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "It's not Cro-Magnons, but these people are hypothesized to have created the oldest known musical instrument, the \"Divje Babe [[div-YEH BAH-beh]] Flute.\" This species' namesake 2010 genome project revealed that non-African <em>homo sapiens</em> often intermixed with this people's \"Altai Mountain\" branch. A valley in Germany names, for ten points, which extinct human species known for protruding foreheads and comparatively shorter limbs than modern humans?", "answer": "<b><u>Neanderthal</u></b>s (accept <em>Homo sapiens</em> <em><b><u>neanderthal</u></b>ensis</em>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Frenchman George Psalmanazar pretended to be from this region in the 18th</u></b> <b><u>century, even constructing an alphabet from scratch and doing odd habits like eating</u></b> <b><u>raw meat with cardamom to prove his foreignness. After expelling the Dutch from this</u></b> <b><u>region, (+)</u> Ming Loyalist Coxinga [[coh-shin-GAH]] established the short-lived Tungning Kingdom in its south during the 17th century. The Urheimat of Austronesian languages is found on this island in the (*) </b>South China Sea. The Chinese Nationalists formed the Republic of China on, for ten points, what East Asian island?", "answer": "<b><u>Taiwan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Formosa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Though it was written for publication in</u> </b><em><b><u>The New York Times Magazine</u></b></em><b><u>, this</u></b> <b><u>document was not published there despite protests from editor Harvey Shapiro. This</u></b> <b><u>document was written in response to \u201cA Call (+)</u> for Unity,\" an open letter by white clergymen referring to this document's author as an \"outsider.\" Claiming \"injustice anywhere is a threat to justice everywhere,\" (*) </b>for ten points, which open letter was written from a cell by Martin Luther King Jr.?", "answer": "<em>Letter from</em> <em><b><u>Birmingham Jail</u></b></em> (accept <em>Letter from</em> <em><b><u>Birmingham City Jail</u></b></em>; or <em><b><u>The</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Negro Is Your Brother</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A memoir set during this war titled</u> </b><em><b><u>Storm of Steel</u></b></em><b><u> was written by Ernst J\u00fcnger</u></b> <b><u>[[YUHN-ger]], the youngest ever winner of the</u> </b><em><b><u>Pour le M\u00e9rite</u></b></em><b><u> [[meh-REET]]. Barbara</u></b> <b><u>Tuchman wrote a Pulitzer Prize-winning historiography of this war titled</u> </b><em><b><u>The Guns</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u></b> <em><b>of August</b></em><b>. Winston Churchill published </b><em><b>The World Crisis</b></em><b> concerning this war, including his own failures during its Dardanelles Campaign at (*) </b>Gallipoli. For ten points, name this early 20th-century war whose literary masterpieces include <em>All Quiet on the Western</em> <em>Front</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>World War One</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Great War</u></b>; accept <b><u>WWI</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Robert Burnell served as chancellor to this king, who enforced substitution as</u></b> <b><u>the only means of alienating lands by the terms of the statute,</u> </b><em><b><u>Quia Emptores</u></b></em><b><u>. Oliver</u></b> <b><u>Cromwell overturned a policy set by this man that removed one ethnic group over</u></b> <b><u>suspicion of blood libel, as well as their practice of usury. The Edict of (+)</u> Expulsion of the Jews was passed by this man, whose forces were defeated at the Battle of Stirling Bridge. This son of Henry III captured and hanged William (*) </b>Wallace of Scotland. For ten points, name this English king who was nicknamed for his height.", "answer": "<b><u>Edward I</u></b> of England (accept <b><u>Edward Longshanks</u></b>; prompt on \"Edward\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After this conflict, the Dikla and Yamit outposts were established in a territory</u></b> <b><u>that was occupied for fifteen years by this war's winner. This conflict erupted a few</u></b> <b><u>weeks after the closure of the Straits of Tiran to shipping, and it included the confused</u></b> <b><u>attack on the (+)</u> </b><em><b>USS Liberty</b></em><b>. Yitzhak Rabin disobeyed orders from Moshe Dayan and advanced into the Gaza Strip during this war, in which the Sinai Peninsula and West Bank was seized by the (*) </b>IGF. For ten points, identify this June 1967 clash between Israel and three Arab states, named for its brief duration.", "answer": "<b><u>Six-Day</u></b> War (or Milhemet <b><u>Sheshet Ha Yamim</u></b>; or an-<b><u>Naksah</u></b>; accept <b><u>June</u></b> War; accept <b><u>Third Arab-Israeli</u></b> War; accept <b><u>1967 Arab-Israeli</u></b> War before \"1967\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Benjamin Franklin Bache's arrest came shortly after the implementation of this</u></b> <b><u>act due to his fiery rhetoric in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Aurora</u></b></em><b><u>. Under these laws, the naturalization period</u></b> <b><u>for some (+)</u> immigrants was changed from five to fourteen years, and non-citizens deemed dangerous could be deported. These laws were adamantly opposed by Jeffersonian Republicans in the Virginia and (*) </b>Kentucky Resolutions. For ten points, name this set of laws that made it harder to become a U.S. citizen and criminalized \"false statements critical of the federal government.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Alien and Sedition</u></b> Acts (accept <b><u>Alien and Sedition</u></b> Laws; prompt on any of the individual laws, such as the \"Naturalization Act,\" the \"Alien Friends Act,\" and the \"Sedition Act\" )", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This park's 50 square mile \"Zone of Death\" is a region where you can</u></b> <b><u>theoretically get away with murder according to a thought experiment by legal scholar</u></b> <b><u>Brian Kalt. Frank Jay Haynes became the official photographer of this park, recording</u></b> <b><u>Rutherford B. (+)</u> Hayes' visit there while fighting poor health. The Washburn Expedition of 1870 explored this parks Upper and Lower Geyser Basin, naming the largest one (*) </b>\"Old Faithful.\" The oldest national park in the U.S. is, for ten points, what nature reserve that lies in Wyoming, Idaho, and Montana?", "answer": "<b><u>Yellowstone</u></b> National Park", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Many native names in this language come from a tradition known as the \"Dream</u></b> <b><u>Name,\" where a name is chosen by a pregnant mother after a visitor appears to her</u></b> <b><u>while asleep. This language, which has an official committee on what children can be</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> named, formed an unusual pidgin with Basque due to Iberian whalers needing to communicate with locals. Snorri Sturluson wrote the </b><em><b>Prose Edda</b></em><b> in an early form of this tongue, describing the creation of the Aesir [[AY-seer]]. Old (*) </b>Norse is most-closely related to, for ten points, what Germanic language spoken in Reykjav\u00edk?", "answer": "<b><u>Icelandic</u></b> (or <b><u>Islenska</u></b>; prompt on \"Old Norse\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this nation, the 2007 April Unrest occurred due to the relocation of a</u></b> <b><u>memorial to fallen Red Army soldiers, resulting in this nation's Moscow embassy being</u></b> <b><u>besieged for a week. The domination of this state's Vaps Movement led to to a period</u></b> <b><u>dubbed the (+)</u> \"Era of Silence,\" and its president, Konstantin P\u00e4ts, formally submitted to a Soviet ultimatum of occupation in 1940. With (*) </b>Lithuania and Latvia, this country achieved a non-violent independence during the Singing Revolution. For ten points, name this Baltic state that was once the target of the Livonian Crusade.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Estonia</u></b> (or <b><u>Eesti</u></b> Vabariik)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}